A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Henry A. Wise, 1856-1859
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Henry A. Wise Executive Papers, 1856-1859
Library of Virginia
36710
10.95 cubic feet (24 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition information unavailable.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 4193-4220.
Miscellaneous Reel 4193 - 1856 January-February 21
Miscellaneous Reel 4194 - 1856 February 22-April 15
Miscellaneous Reel 4195 - 1856 April 16-June 13
Miscellaneous Reel 4196 - 1856 June 14-August 14
Miscellaneous Reel 4197 - 1856 August 15-October 15
Miscellaneous Reel 4198 - 1856 October 16-December 10
Miscellaneous Reel 4199 - 1856 December 11-1857 January 31
Miscellaneous Reel 4200 - 1857 February 1-March 20
Miscellaneous Reel 4201 - 1857 March 21-May 10
Miscellaneous Reel 4202 - 1857 May 11-July 10
Miscellaneous Reel 4203 - 1857 July 11-September 11
Miscellaneous Reel 4204 - 1857 September 12-November 19
Miscellaneous Reel 4205 - 1857 November 20-1858 January 11
Miscellaneous Reel 4206 - 1858 January 12-March 15
Miscellaneous Reel 4207 - 1858 March 16-April 30
Miscellaneous Reel 4208 - 1858 May 1-June 30
Miscellaneous Reel 4209 - 1858 July 1-September 13
Miscellaneous Reel 4210 - 1858 September 14-October 31
Miscellaneous Reel 4211 - 1858 November 1-December 31
Miscellaneous Reel 4212 - 1859 January 1-February 23
Miscellaneous Reel 4213 - 1859 February 24-April (Pardons)
Miscellaneous Reel 4214 - 1859 May 1-June 26
Miscellaneous Reel 4215 - 1859 June 26-August 31
Miscellaneous Reel 4216 - 1859 August (Pardons)-October (Pardons)
Miscellaneous Reel 4217 - 1859 November 1-December (Pardons)
Miscellaneous Reel 4218 - Undated-Monroe Interment/John Brown's Raid, 1859 October 17-November 20
Miscellaneous Reel 4219 - John Brown's Raid, 1859 November 21-December 6
Miscellaneous Reel 4220 - John Brown's Raid, 1859 December 8-31 & Clippings-Orders
Biographical Information
Governor Henry Alexander Wise was born in Accomack County, Virginia, in 1806. The son of Major John Wise, a member of the House of Delegates, and Sarah Corbin Cropper, Henry Wise was the fifth child of his father's second marriage. Wise attended Washington College in Washington, Pa., and later studied law at Judge Tucker's law school in Winchester, Va. He married Ann Jennings in 1828 and moved to Nashville, Tenn., to practice law. He returned to Accomack County in 1831 and entered into politics serving in Congress from 1833-1844 as a Jacksonian Democrat. Wise was nominated as United States Minister to Brazil on January 18, 1844. He was officially appointed by President John Tyler, February 16, 1844, as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the United States to Brazil until August 1847. He was elected as a delegate to the Constitutional Convention of 1850. Wise defeated Thomas Flournoy of the Know Nothing Party in the gubernatorial election of 1855 and served as governor of Virginia from 1856 until 1859. Probably the most important event in his governorship was the raid on the federal arsenal at Harper's Ferry by abolitionist John Brown in 1859 and Brown's subsequent execution. After his governorship, Wise contributed to the Virginia Convention of 1861 in which the state seceeded from the Union and later was commissioned to form the "Wise Legion" during the Civil War. After the war, he resumed his law practice in Richmond and died on September 12, 1876.
Scope and Content Information
Governor Wise's Executive papers are organized into two series. Series have been designated for Chronological files and Subject files. The bulk of the material can be found in the Chronological files series which documents the day-to-day work of the governor from 1856 to 1859. Correspondence, court cases, pollbooks, pardons, receipts, clippings, reports, petitions, proclamations, requisitions, resolutions, and other items can be found in this series. The correspondence is primarily incoming and represents an array of concerns and issues. Noteworthy correspondents include Secretary of War, Jefferson Davis (March 10, 1856 & Oct. 8, 1856), Rembrandt Peale (Nov. 22, 1858), and former President John Tyler (Nov. 4, 1859). In addition, correspondence from George Washington Lewis, ancestor of George Washington, concerns the proposed sale of Mt. Vernon and Wakefield, the ancestral home of George Washington, to the State of Virginia. Correspondence from Charles Dimmock, Commandant of the Public Guard, concerns the erection of the Washington Monument in Capital Square (Jan.-Feb., 1858).
More substantial and significant, however, are the materials related to John Brown's Raid on Harper's Ferry in 1859. The majority of this series consists of correspondence asking for the pardon, commutation of punishment, or execution of John Brown. Many of the letters threaten the life of the governor and the invasion of Virginia in the event of John Brown's execution. Subject files located to the rear of the series contain intercepted correspondence to John Brown; correspondence from detectives pursuing escaped conspirators; correspondence by Charles P. Tidd, a conspirator with John Brown; and correspondence of Andrew Hunter, the prosecutor in the case agianst John Brown. In addition, there are receipts and vouchers of various expenses incurred by militia units, etc., during the raid.
Much of the correspondence consists of recommendations of Virginians to the governor for appointments. The governor appointed coroners; inspectors of tobacco, vessels, and lumber; auditors of public accounts; commissioners; Bank of Virginia directors; and notaries, to name a few. Numerous petitions accompany these recommendations. Letters by individuals stating their desire to be considered for a particular position are also present. One such letter documents J.E.B. Stuart's application to the Virginia Military Institutes's Board of Visitors (April 29, 1859). The governor also issued commissions for various elected positions such as justice of the peace, etc. As a result, pollbooks, which provide the results of the elections, are contained in the executive papers.
An important function of the governor was issuing reprieves and pardons. Copies of court cases, clippings, petitions, and correspondence supplement the pardons. Note that some of the pardons in 1859 are filed separately. The governor both received and issued proclamations and requisitions regarding escaped convicts and fugitives. Also found in the executive papers are reports from various state agents such as the Superintendent of the Western Lunatic Asylum, Commissioner of Tobacco Warehouses in Richmond, Superintendent of the Penitentiary, etc. Resolutions from other states concern boundary issues with Virginia and many relate to the Dred Scott decision and the expansion of slavery in the Western states.
The second series of Governor Wise's Executive papers contains subject files. Only two subjects are represented in this series: Monroe's Interment and John Brown's Raid. One folder of papers regarding the removal of President James Monroe's remains from New York to Hollywood Cemetery (Richmond, Va.) has been separated from the chronological files. This folder includes correspondence between the Mayor of New York City, the President of Hollywood Cemetery, and Governor Wise. It also includes proposals for a mausoleum to hold Monroe's remains.
Organization
Organized into two series: I: Chronological files, 1856-1859. II: Subject files, 1858-1859.
Contents List
- Chronological Files
  - 1856, January 1-15 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1856, January 16-24 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1856, January 25-31 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1856, February 1-16 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1856, February 17-21 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1856, February 22-29 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1856, March 1-14 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1856, March 15-26 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1856, March 27-31 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1856, April 1-5 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1856, April 6-15 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1856, April 16-30 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1856, May 1-9 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1856, May 10-22 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1856, May 23-31 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1856, June 1-13 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1856, June 14-30 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1856, July 1-13 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1856, July 14-30 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1856, August 1-14 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1856, August 15-31 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1856, September 1-5 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1856, September 6-15 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1856, September 16-30 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1856, October 1-15 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1856, October 16-26 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1856, October 27-31 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1856, November 1-10 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1856, November 11-29 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1856, December 1-10 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1856, December 11-20 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1856, December 21-31 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1857, January 1-12 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1857, January 13-31 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1857, February 1-13 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1857, February 14-28 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1857, March 2-6 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1857, March 7-20 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1857, March 21-31 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1857, April 1-8 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1857, April 9-23 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1857, April 24-30 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1857, May 1-20 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1857, May 21-30 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1857, June 1-15 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1857, June 16-22 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1857, June 23-30 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1857, July 1-10 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1857, July 11-19 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1857, July 20-31 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1857, August 1-21 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1857, August 22-31 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1857, September 1-11 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1857, September 12-23 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1857, September 24-30 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1857, October 1-15 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1857, October 16-31 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1857, November 2-19 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1857, November 20-30 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1857, December 1-7 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1857, December 8-22 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1857, December 23-31 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1858, January 1-11 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 1858, January 12-15 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 1858, January 16-30 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 1858, February 1-15 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 1858, February 16-27 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 1858, March 1-5 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 1858, March 16-23 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1858, March 24-31 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 1858, April 1-7 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 1858, April 8-19 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 1858, April 20-30 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 1858, May 1-7 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 1858, May 8-17 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1858, May 18-28 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 1858, May 29-31 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 1858, June 1-10 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 1858, June 11-21 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 1858, June 22-30 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 1858, July 1-13 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 1858, July 14-27 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 8)
  - 1858, July 28-31 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 1858, August 1-10 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 1858, August 11-26 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 1858, August 27-31 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 1858, September 1-13 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 1858, September 14-17 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 1858, September 18-27 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 7)
  - 1858, September 28-30 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 8)
  - 1858, October 1-10 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 1)
  - 1858, October 11-20 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 2)
  - 1858, October 21-31 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 3)
  - 1858, November 1-10 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 4)
  - 1858, November 11-30 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 5)
  - 1858, December 1-10 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 6)
  - 1858, December 11-31 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 7)
  - 1859, January 1-12 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 1)
  - 1859, January 13-21 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 2)
  - 1859, January 22-31 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 3)
  - 1859, February 1-10 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 4)
  - 1859, February 11-23 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 5)
  - 1859, February 24-28 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 6)
  - 1859, March 1-22 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 1)
  - 1859, March 23-31 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 2)
  - 1859, March - Pardons (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 3)
  - 1859, April 1-20 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 4)
  - 1859, April 21-29 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 5)
  - 1859, April - Pardons (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 6)
  - 1859, May 1-9 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 7)
  - 1859, May 10-16 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 8)
  - 1859, May 17-25 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 1)
  - 1859, May 26-31 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 2)
  - 1859, June 1-15 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 3)
  - 1859, June 16-26 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 4)
  - 1859, June 26 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 5)
  - 1859, June 26-30 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 6)
  - 1859, July 1-15 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 7)
  - 1859, July 16-31 (Box-folder Box 19, Folder 1)
  - 1859, July - Pardons (Box-folder Box 19, Folder 2)
  - 1859, August 1-10 (Box-folder Box 19, Folder 3)
  - 1859, August 11-31 (Box-folder Box 19, Folder 4)
  - 1859, August - Pardons (Box-folder Box 19, Folder 5)
  - 1859, September 1-20 (Box-folder Box 19, Folder 6)
  - 1859, September 21-30 (Box-folder Box 19, Folder 7)
  - 1859, September - Pardons (Box-folder Box 19, Folder 8)
  - 1859, October 1-19 (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 1)
  - 1859, October 20-31 (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 2)
  - 1859, October - Pardons (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 1859, November 1-25 (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 4)
  - 1859, November 26-30 (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 5)
  - 1859, November - Pardons (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 6)
  - 1859, December 1-20 (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 7)
  - 1859, December 21-31 (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 8)
  - 1859, December - Pardons (Box-folder Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Undated (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 1)
- Subject Files
  - Monroe's Interment, May 19-July 7, 1958 (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 2)
  - John Brown's Raid, October-December 1859
    - 1859, October 17-26 (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 3)
    - 1859, October 27-31 (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 4)
    - 1859, November 1-5 (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 5)
    - 1859, November 6-10 (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 6)
    - 1859, November 11-15 (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 7)
    - 1859, November 16-20 (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 8)
    - 1859, November 21-24 (Box-folder Box 21, Folder 9)
    - 1859, November 25-27 (Box-folder Box 22, Folder 1)
    - 1859, November 28-30 (Box-folder Box 22, Folder 2)
    - 1859, December 1-2 (Box-folder Box 22, Folder 3)
    - 1859, December 5-7 (Box-folder Box 22, Folder 4)
    - 1859, December 8-14 (Box-folder Box 22, Folder 5)
    - 1859, December 15-22 (Box-folder Box 22, Folder 6)
    - 1859, December 23-31 (Box-folder Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Undated (Box-folder Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Clippings (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - Detectives (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - Hunter, Andrew (Prosecutor) (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - Intercepted Letters (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - Tidd, Charles P. (Conspirator) (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Expenses - General (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Expenses - Hospital & Sick (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Expenses - Pay Rolls (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Expenses - Purchase of Arms (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Expenses - Quartermaster (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Orders (Box-folder Box 23, Folder 12)